<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section id="sect-Defensive_Coding-CXX-Std">
  <title>The C++ standard library</title>
  <para>
    The C++ standard library includes most of its C counterpart
    by reference, see <xref linkend="sect-Defensive_Coding-C-Libc"/>.
  </para>
  <section id="sect-Defensive_Coding-CXX-Std-String">
    <title>String handling with <literal>std::string</literal></title>
    <para>
      The <literal>std::string</literal> class provides a convenient
      way to handle strings.  Unlike C strings,
      <literal>std::string</literal> objects have an explicit length
      (and can contain embedded NUL characters), and storage for its
      characters is managed automatically.  This section discusses
      <literal>std::string</literal>, but these observations also
      apply to other instances of the
      <literal>std::basic_string</literal> template.
    </para>
    <para>
      The pointer returned by the <function>data()</function> member
      function does not necessarily point to a NUL-terminated string.
      To obtain a C-compatible string pointer, use
      <function>c_str()</function> instead, which adds the NUL
      terminator.
    </para>
    <para>
      The pointers returned by the <function>data()</function> and
      <function>c_str()</function> functions and iterators are only
      valid until certain events happen.  It is required that the
      exact <literal>std::string</literal> object still exists (even
      if it was initially created as a copy of another string object).
      Pointers and iterators are also invalidated when non-const
      member functions are called, or functions with a non-const
      reference parameter.  The behavior of the GCC implementation
      deviates from that required by the C++ standard if multiple
      threads are present.  In general, only the first call to a
      non-const member function after a structural modification of the
      string (such as appending a character) is invalidating, but this
      also applies to member function such as the non-const version of
      <function>begin()</function>, in violation of the C++ standard.
    </para>
    <para>
      Particular care is necessary when invoking the
      <function>c_str()</function> member function on a temporary
      object.  This is convenient for calling C functions, but the
      pointer will turn invalid as soon as the temporary object is
      destroyed, which generally happens when the outermost expression
      enclosing the expression on which <function>c_str()</function>
      is called completes evaluation.  Passing the result of
      <function>c_str()</function> to a function which does not store
      or otherwise leak that pointer is safe, though.
    </para>
    <para>
      Like with <literal>std::vector</literal> and
      <literal>std::array</literal>, subscribing with
      <literal>operator[]</literal> does not perform bounds checks.
      Use the <function>at(size_type)</function> member function
      instead.  See <xref
      linkend="sect-Defensive_Coding-CXX-Std-Subscript"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Never write to the pointers returned by
      <function>data()</function> or <function>c_str()</function>
      after casting away <literal>const</literal>.  If you need a
      C-style writable string, use a
      <literal>std::vector&lt;char&gt;</literal> object and its
      <function>data()</function> member function.  In this case, you
      have to explicitly add the terminating NUL character.
    </para>
    <para>
      GCC's implementation of <literal>std::string</literal> is
      currently based on reference counting.  It is expected that a
      future version will remove the reference counting, due to
      performance and conformance issues.  As a result, code that
      implicitly assumes sharing by holding to pointers or iterators
      for too long will break, resulting in run-time crashes or worse.
      On the other hand, non-const iterator-returning functions will
      no longer give other threads an opportunity for invalidating
      existing iterators and pointers because iterator invalidation
      does not depend on sharing of the internal character array
      object anymore.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Defensive_Coding-CXX-Std-Subscript">
    <title>Containers and <literal>operator[]</literal></title>
    <para>
      Many sequence containers similar to <literal>std::vector</literal>
      provide both <literal>operator[](size_type)</literal> and a
      member function <literal>at(size_type)</literal>.  This applies
      to <literal>std::vector</literal> itself,
      <literal>std::array</literal>, <literal>std::string</literal>
      and other instances of <literal>std::basic_string</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <literal>operator[](size_type)</literal> is not required by the
      standard to perform bounds checking (and the implementation in
      GCC does not).  In contrast, <literal>at(size_type)</literal>
      must perform such a check.  Therefore, in code which is not
      performance-critical, you should prefer
      <literal>at(size_type)</literal> over
      <literal>operator[](size_type)</literal>, even though it is
      slightly more verbose.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Defensive_Coding-CXX-Std-Iterators">
    <title>Iterators</title>
    <para>
      Iterators do not perform any bounds checking.  Therefore, all
      functions that work on iterators should accept them in pairs,
      denoting a range, and make sure that iterators are not moved
      outside that range.  For forward iterators and bidirectional
      iterators, you need to check for equality before moving the
      first or last iterator in the range.  For random-access
      iterators, you need to compute the difference before adding or
      subtracting an offset.  It is not possible to perform the
      operation and check for an invalid operator afterwards.
    </para>
    <para>
      Output iterators cannot be compared for equality.  Therefore, it
      is impossible to write code that detects that it has been
      supplied an output area that is too small, and their use should
      be avoided.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

