<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="chap-Defensive_Coding-Go">
<title>The Go Programming Language</title>
<para>
  This chapter contains language-specific recommendations for Go.
</para>
<section id="chap-Defensive_Coding-Go-Memory_Safety">
  <title>Memory safety</title>
  <para>
    Go provides memory safety, but only if the program is not executed
    in parallel (that is, <envar>GOMAXPROCS</envar> is not larger than
    <literal>1</literal>).  The reason is that interface values and
    slices consist of multiple words are not updated atomically.
    Another thread of execution can observe an inconsistent pairing
    between type information and stored value (for interfaces) or
    pointer and length (for slices), and such inconsistency can lead
    to a memory safety violation.
  </para>
  <para>
    Code which does not run in parallel and does not use the
    <literal>unsafe</literal> package (or other packages which expose
    unsafe constructs) is memory-safe.  For example, invalid casts and
    out-of-range subscripting cause panics and run time.
  </para>
  <para>
    Keep in mind that finalization can introduce parallelism because
    finalizers are executed concurrently, potentially interleaved with
    the rest of the program.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="chap-Defensive_Coding-Go-Error_Handling">
  <title>Error handling</title>
  <para>
    Only a few common operations (such as pointer dereference, integer
    division, array subscripting) trigger exceptions in Go, called
    <emphasis>panics</emphasis>.  Most interfaces in the standard
    library use a separate return value of type
    <literal>error</literal> to signal error.
  </para>
  <para>
    Not checking error return values can lead to incorrect operation
    and data loss (especially in the case of writes, using interfaces
    such as <literal>io.Writer</literal>).
  </para>
  <para>
    The correct way to check error return values depends on the
    function or method being called.  In the majority of cases, the
    first step after calling a function should be an error check
    against the <literal>nil</literal> value, handling any encountered
    error.  See <xref
    linkend="ex-Defensive_Coding-Go-Error_Handling-Regular"/> for
    details.
  </para>
  <example id="ex-Defensive_Coding-Go-Error_Handling-Regular">
    <title>Regular error handling in Go</title>
    <xi:include href="snippets/Go-Error_Handling-Regular.xml"
		xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </example>
  <para>
    However, with <literal>io.Reader</literal>,
    <literal>io.ReaderAt</literal> and related interfaces, it is
    necessary to check for a non-zero number of read bytes first, as
    shown in <xref
    linkend="ex-Defensive_Coding-Go-Error_Handling-IO"/>.  If this
    pattern is not followed, data loss may occur.  This is due to the
    fact that the <literal>io.Reader</literal> interface permits
    returning both data and an error at the same time.
  </para>
  <example id="ex-Defensive_Coding-Go-Error_Handling-IO">
    <title>Read error handling in Go</title>
    <xi:include href="snippets/Go-Error_Handling-IO.xml"
		xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </example>
</section>
<section id="chap-Defensive_Coding-Go-Garbage_Collector">
  <title>Garbage Collector</title>
  <para>
    Older Go releases (before Go 1.3) use a conservative garbage
    collector without blacklisting.  This means that data blobs can
    cause retention of unrelated data structures because the data is
    conservatively interpreted as pointers.  This phenomenon can be
    triggered accidentally on 32-bit architectures and is more likely
    to occur if the heap grows larger.  On 64-bit architectures, it
    may be possible to trigger it deliberately—it is unlikely to occur
    spontaneously.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="chap-Defensive_Coding-Go-Marshaling">
  <title>Marshaling and marshaling</title>
  <para>
    Several packages in the <literal>encoding</literal> hierarchy
    provide support for serialization and deserialization.  The usual
    caveats apply (see
    <xref linkend="chap-Defensive_Coding-Tasks-Serialization"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
    As an additional precaution, the <function>Unmarshal</function>
    and <function>Decode</function> functions should only be used with
    fresh values in the <literal>interface{}</literal> argument.  This
    is due to the way defaults for missing values are implemented:
    During deserialization, missing value do not result in an error,
    but the original value is preserved.  Using a fresh value (with
    suitable default values if necessary) ensures that data from a
    previous deserialization operation does not leak into the current
    one.  This is especially relevant when structs are deserialized.
  </para>
</section>
</chapter>
